[MUSIC PLAYING]
BRIAN YU: Welcome back, everyone, to Web
Programming with Python and JavaScript.
Today we're going to continue
where we left off from last week.
So last week, if you recall, we
talked about Git, a version control
tool that lets us manage
different versions of our project,
and keep track whenever we make
new changes to our project,
and let us look back at the history of
changes that we made to our project.
And then we also took
a look at HTML, which
let us lay out a website
how we wanted to,
as well as CSS, or
Cascading Style Sheets,
which allowed us to take a web page,
and style it in different ways,
and change the aesthetics of the page
in order to make it look the way that we
want it to look.
So this week we'll dive more
in-depth into all three of those,
focusing especially on HTML
and CSS, and taking a look
at how we can leverage these
tools and some other tools
to help make our websites
even more dynamic
to help them be designed the way
that we want them to be designed.
So the first thing that we'll
take a look at is go back to Git.
So if you remember from
last week, Git was a tool
that we were using in
order to keep track
of different versions of our project.
And in particular, as we work on a
project and continue to make changes,
the term we used in Git was to
make commits to our project.
So we might start with
a first commit that
just contains initial files that
we had when we started the project.
And as we continue to work on
the project and add new features,
it's a good idea, when working
with a version control system
like Git, to frequently make
commits when we make a new change,
save those changes such that,
later, we can refer back
to them via a commit message
that describes what changed
in this particular version
so that later on, we
have a history of all
of the changes that were
made to the project at any given time.
So we might continue to making changes.
And what you might imagine is that
this chain of different commits
might start to get pretty long.
So maybe we have a working project
at this stage in the program,
and we want to add a new feature to
our web application, for example.
So at this point, we might
start working on a new feature
here by adding another commit.
We might make more progress on that new
feature, keep working on that feature.
But what if, at this point, while
we're midway through working
on some new feature to our
existing web application,
we realized that there was some sort
of bug, some bug in our web application
that occurred way back here that we want
to quickly fix, so that we can ship out
a new fix so that people aren't
sitting with that bug for a long time?
Well, this linear structure where,
every time we make changes, we just
save those changes one
after another, that
makes it pretty challenging to
say, I want to fix a bug back here.
We could, of course, reset, and go
back to this stage, and fix the bug,
and then keep working
on the new feature.
But we've already made these
new changes to the new feature.
So it sort of starts to get a
little bit messy at this point.
So Git has this in mind
when it was first designed.
And so that's why Git has
a tool called branching.
And what branching
effectively allows us to do
is, rather than just have
a single linear progression
of the entire project where each
change always follows on the change
immediately before it, and that's
the only path that we have to follow,
branching lets us take our project
in multiple different directions.
It lets us maintain one branch
that will be our "master"
branch, the original version of our code
that's supposedly the version that's
always usable, and then lets us have
other branches that allow us to work
on different features that are
still in progress, and later,
take those branches and work
them into the original code.
So to take an example, we might
start with that same first commit
and still continue to make changes.
But when we're in a stable place and
we want to try to add a new feature
and start working on that new
feature, rather than just add
that feature immediately after it,
what we can do is we can branch off,
begin a new branch, and
say, OK, let's start
working on this new feature
in a separate branch
from the original
project, and keep working
on that new feature on
that other separate branch.
Then, at this point, if we come to
that same realization, the realization
that, oh, way back here, there
was some bug in the code, some bug
that we would want to fix, rather
than try and reset, and go back
here, and figure out how to get
back to where we were before,
we can just switch back over to
this branch, fix the bug there.
And that way, we're in
a position where we now
have these two separate branches,
this one original branch that
has that fixed bug, and
then this other branch
whereby we started
working on a new feature,
and we kept working on a new feature.
And this is especially
helpful if it's not just you
that's working on the web application.
If you and multiple other teammates are
also working on the same application,
you might imagine this
as saying, you are
working on one branch going off in
one direction working on the project.
And some other person, some
collaborator you're working with,
is sort of going off in
a different direction,
working on some different feature,
but also on the same project.
And later, when you're ready, you
can do what Git calls "merging"--
in other words, taking
two separate branches
and then combining them together.
So we might label these branches.
This is what we would
generally call the master
branch, which is the default branch,
the original branch that we started out
with.
And then these other branches,
you can have as many as you want.
You can name them whatever you want.
In this case, I've just
called this branch "feature"
to represent the fact that
this is a branch that's
representing a new feature that
we would want to potentially add
to this existing web application.
Git also has a bit of additional
terminology that's useful to know.
Git uses the capital phrase "HEAD"
to refer to where we currently
are in the repository.
So if you're working on the project and
you're currently working on the master
branch, then HEAD points to master.
In other words, where you are
in the repository right now
is the master branch.
That's the code you're working with.
But Git makes it very easy
to change where HEAD is.
If you wanted to go
to the feature branch,
or "check out" the feature branch, as
Git would use with its terminology,
you could very easily check
out the feature branch
moving the HEAD to the feature branch.
And now you can continue
working on that feature.
And so only when you feel
comfortable with the feature, when
you feel comfortable with the bug fixes
can you then merge the two together
by having another commit that combines
two previous branches and merges
them back together into one.
And so this concept of Git
branching is very helpful
whether you are working on different
parts of your own web application
and have different features
that are happening at once
that you want to develop separately
but then combine together later,
or if you and collaborators are
working together on a project
where it's very easy for you
to work without having to worry
about what someone else is doing.
And only when you're both ready
with your separate features
do you then want to merge
them together and figure out
how to resolve any conflicts
that might come about where
you and another collaborator
have potentially
edited the same line of the same
file, for example, that you can then
deal with by resolving those merge
conflicts like we saw last week.
So we'll take a look at an
example of that just to give you
a sense for how this would
actually work on the command line
and how we would actually do branching.
So I have, here, a Lecture 1 repository.
And right now, inside of Lecture 1
is just a file called index.html.
So index.html is, right now, just a
test website that has title as "Test."
And inside the body is
just the word "test."
This is just a sample website
that we're going to use
to demonstrate the idea of branching.
So maybe I'm going to make
a commit to this file.
Instead of saying "test" in the body,
let's say something a little bit nicer.
Let's say "Hello, world!"
So I've changed the message in the body.
And now, on the command line,
I'm going to git add index.html.
I've made changes to index.html.
These are changes that I want to track
the next time that I make a commit.
And now I can say git commit -m.
I want to leave a message
when I make this commit.
And in this case, I want to
say I changed the body message.
So that's the change that I just made.
Again, Git counts that as
one insertion, one deletion.
And so that commit is now
made to this repository.
But now say I want to test
something a little bit different.
I want to try something
different, and I don't want
to mess up my original master branch.
Well, if I type "git branch" right
now and press Return, what you'll see
is a listing of all of the branches
that are currently on my repository.
And right now it's just
this one branch, master.
So that's the only branch that I have.
But if I want to create
a new branch, it's
as simple as saying "git branch"
followed by the name of some new branch
that I want to add.
So I want to add a new
feature to my website.
I might call that branch the
feature branch, for example.
So I press Return.
And nothing seems to happen.
But if I type "git branch" again to say,
OK, let's take a look at the branches
that I currently have in this
repository, what are they,
I'll see that we have a master branch,
and we also have this feature branch.
And the fact that the master branch is
highlighted in green and has the star
next to it tells me that this is the
current branch that I'm currently on,
and this feature branch
is some other branch.
So let's say I now want to
move to the feature branch
and start working on that.
So I might say "git checkout," where
"checkout" is the term that Git
uses for saying, I want
to move where I currently
am in the repository to somewhere else.
Right now I'm on the master branch.
I want to move to the
feature branch, for example.
And so if I press Return here, it says
"Switched to branch 'feature.'" And
if I type "git branch" again
here, you'll see that, now,
feature branch is the one
that's highlighted in green.
It's the one with the star next to it.
That is now the branch
that I'm currently on.
If I go back to the index.html file,
nothing really seems to have changed.
But now I can start to say,
OK, let's add in a new feature.
So here is a new feature, just another
line to the website in this case.
But I can go ahead and
add and commit that.
And a quick trick that we
talked about briefly last week
is that you can say "git commit -am"
to combine the git add step and the git
commit step into one step. git commit
-am just says, add all of the files
that I've changed that
I've already been tracking,
and commit them at the same time.
Just combines those two
steps into one in case
you want to be a little more efficient.
And now I added another line.
So that's the change
that I just made there.
And that's now on my feature branch,
right, where I have "Hello, world!"
and "Here is a new feature."
If I were to--
now, if my current branches
are feature and master,
if I were to check out the master branch
again, go back to the master branch
before, what you'll notice is that,
now that I'm back on branch master
and I go back to
index.html, this file now
shows me the version of the file that is
on the master branch that only has this
"Hello, world!" line and doesn't
have that second line that I added,
which means that that other
change isn't on the master branch.
It's only on the feature branch.
And as a result, it's not
going to be represented here.
I can see that even more
clearly using a command
that we learned last
week, git log, which
shows me the history
of all of the commits
that I've made on a particular branch.
If I, here, now, on the master
branch, type in "git log" for example,
you'll see, here was my first file.
And here I changed the body message.
But those are the only two changes
that I made on this particular branch.
If I checkout the feature branch
instead, switch to that branch,
and type "git log" again,
you'll see that now there
are three commits on this branch.
There was the first file, the change
to the body message, and the fact
that I added another line there as well.
And so this goes to show
that different branches can
have different commits
working on them, so
to touch that you can be
working on different features
separately without needing
to worry about what's
happening on a different branch.
So now we've been working
on these separately.
Now we want to combine
them back together.
So let me go ahead and switch
back to the masker branch.
And remember now, in the master
branch, it just says "Hello, world!"
just the simple message.
If I now want to take what was
previously on the feature branch
and merge it into the master
branch, while on the master branch,
I'm going to type "git merge"
followed by the name of the branch
that I want to merge in.
In this case, that's the feature branch.
And that's saying, take those commits
that are on the feature branch,
and let's merge them
into the master branch.
So git merge feature--
one file changed.
There was one insertion.
That makes sense.
And now, even though I'm on my
master branch, if I check the file,
I see that second additional
line that was added there.
And so different branches
can work separately.
But when I'm ready, I can
merge those changes together.
In this case, it was
a very simple change.
But sometimes those changes
could be more complicated
and might require resolving
those merge conflicts.
But that allows you to assist
yourself in the development
process whether you're working alone
or with collaborators, just to make
that process a little bit easier.
Questions about branching or merging?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
BRIAN YU: Correct.
Great question.
So the question is, if I create
a branch on my computer, what
happens to the GitHub repository where
I originally cloned the code from?
So the answer to that question
is, when I create a branch locally
on my own computer, it
only exists on my computer.
It doesn't yet exist on GitHub
until I push it to GitHub in order
to tell GitHub that
that new branch exists.
And in fact, we can show you that.
I'll show you that right now actually.
So if I--
I'm going to go ahead and
reset what I did before.
I'm just going to remove
the lecture1 repository.
And we'll just restart it, just
to give you a demonstration.
If I go to
github.com/student50/lecture1,
this is the GitHub page
for this repository.
And I want to clone this repository.
I'm just starting from scratch here.
I'll go to the Clone or Download button.
I'll take this link, copy it, and then
say "git clone" followed by that link.
That's going to clone
the lecture1 repository.
And if I go into the
lecture1 repository,
I only have a master branch.
But now let's say I want
to add a new branch.
Let's add a feature branch.
And on this feature branch, I'm going
to first checkout the feature branch
so that I'm on the feature branch.
And now I'm going to say--
let's go ahead and open up index.html.
Right now it just says "Test."
This was the original
contents of that repository.
I'm going to change that to say
"Here is the new branch contents."
So this is the new version that I
want to add to this feature branch.
And I'll go ahead and git add
index.html and commit that change--
so "New branch contents."
And now if I try to git push--
remember, before, that
git push is the command
that I use to take the changes
that I made on my computer
and make them reflect on GitHub--
you'll notice that what I get
is this strange message that
says "The current branch
feature has no upstream branch."
And what that means is that I've created
a new branch, feature, on my computer.
But there is no corresponding branch on
GitHub that I can push to yet, right?
GitHub only has a master branch.
And on my computer, I have both a
master branch and a feature branch.
So if I want to push to GitHub and
say, all right, push to GitHub,
but push to a new branch
on GitHub called feature,
then I'll run this command
here, git push --set-upstream.
So when I push up to GitHub, what
branch do I want to push it to?
And I want to push it
to the feature branch.
So that's just copying
this command right here.
And so when I do that, I have now
pushed that new branch up to GitHub.
And if I refresh this page--
or even if I don't refresh--
it tells me that I've pushed
a new branch, feature.
And I can click on that feature branch
to see that, on the feature branch,
I have the new branch contents.
But if I switch from the feature
branch back to the master branch,
this just has the
original test contents.
So you can take your existing
branches and push them to GitHub
as well such that GitHub can help
manage all of those branches too.
Other questions about Git,
branching, or merging?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
BRIAN YU: Yeah.
So if you look at the
URL here in GitHub,
it tells you the name
of the person who owns
the repository, the name
of the repository itself.
And then, here is master, which
is just the name of the branch
that I'm currently on.
And so when you navigate
through GitHub's user interface,
you will see the different names
of the branches show up in the URL
as you go to different pages.
AUDIENCE: On the front page.
BRIAN YU: Oh, so the question is,
what happens on the front page?
On the front page, by default, there's
a default branch that GitHub uses.
And usually that's the master branch.
You have the ability to change what
that default original branch is.
But generally speaking, it
will be the master branch.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
BRIAN YU: Oh, OK.
So the question is, in project 0,
we're working with GitHub Pages, which
lets us take websites and
deploy them to the internet
just by pushing them
to a GitHub repository.
The way that GitHub Pages
works is that it's only
deploying to the internet
from a particular branch.
So when you set up GitHub Pages in
the Settings page of your repository,
you had to tell GitHub,
I want to upload files
to the internet based on the contents
of the master branch, for example.
Or you could specify
which branch you wanted.
And so as a result, anything
that's on any other branch
isn't going to be
reflected on the internet
if you just go to the
GitHub Pages website.
What you'll need to do is
test the changes on your own
on your own computer.
And when you feel
comfortable with them, when
those are the changes that you
want to deploy to the internet,
then you can merge them
into the master branch.
And that will be what ultimately
gets deployed to the internet.
Other questions about Git,
or GitHub, or branches?
OK.
A couple other topics just
to talk about briefly--
so these were sort of
the key commands that we
were using when regarding to branching
in Git. git branch, If we don't
have anything after it, just
shows us all of the branches
that we currently have.
If we have git branch followed
by the name of a branch,
that creates a new branch.
git checkout lets us change where
we currently are in the repository.
We can change from one
branch to another branch,
or even one commit to another commit.
And then, git merge allows us
to take two separate branches
and combine them back together.
OK, so a couple other
things to talk about--
next is the concept of remotes.
This is something we've
already been using.
But we haven't really looked
at how exactly it's working.
The concept of Git
remotes is just the idea
that we can have a version
of the repository that's
stored somewhere else on the computer,
in particular-- or stored somewhere
else on the internet, in
particular-- on GitHub,
for instance, if we're cloning
the repository from GitHub.
And so if you've been working with
GitHub in project 0, for example,
and you keep seeing the
word "origin" show up--
it showed up just a moment ago when
I was trying to push to a new branch,
for example--
that origin is just
the name of a remote,
a version of the repository
that lives somewhere else.
I have one version of the
repository on my computer,
and the remote is some
version of the repository that
exists on GitHub, for example.
And so how does that work?
Well, I have some
version of the repository
that, maybe, has four commits on it.
And this is the remote
version, the version on GitHub,
that might be a little bit later.
And both my version of the
repository and the remote
both have their own branches.
We saw before that I might have two
branches even though GitHub might only
have one branch going on.
And this branch might be further
along in terms of the commit history
than my current branch is.
And so if I wanted to work with this
remote version of the repository, what
I might do is run a command called
git fetch, which just means,
go to the remote, this online
version of the repository,
and download all of the latest commits.
And so when I run git
fetch, it's going to take
those commits from the origin, this
version of the repository stored
on GitHub, and download
them locally so that, now, I
have this origin/master branch, the
master branch from my origin remote.
And I have my current master
branch, which is still here.
So master is where I
am in my repository.
And so if, now, I want my master branch
to be updated to reflect the latest
changes, the command to
do that is to sort of
say I want to merge where I am
with where origin master is.
And so if you do git
merge origin/master,
that causes your master branch
to be updated to reflect
the latest version of the origin.
But this process is so frequent-- the
process of, download the latest commits
and move myself to the latest
commit based on the master branch
of the origin--
that these two commands can be
simplified into just the command git
pull.
But if you're ever wondering
what git pull is actually doing,
this is what's happening.
It's downloading, or fetching, the
latest commits from the origin.
And then it's sort of fast-forwarding
yourself on the master branch
to match up with the latest commit
on the origin master branch.
But that's what git pull is doing.
And that's what allows you to
manage that remote repository
and move yourself to the latest version.
OK, couple other concepts that
are sort of specific to GitHub
that may prove useful to you as you
start to work on the projects-- one
is the concept of forks.
So a fork of a repository is
just an entirely separate version
of that repository that gets
copied based off an original.
So what you saw in project 0, if you
started-- or if you haven't started,
you'll take a look at it this week--
is that we create a new
repository for you that's going
to store the contents of project 0.
And the first thing that you'll want to
do is create a fork of that repository
where we have a version of the
repository that belongs to us,
and you are going to
fork it-- in other words,
create an entirely separate version of
that repository that belongs to you.
And so on that fork that you own,
you can do whatever you want to it.
You can add new branches, you can
push to it, you can pull from it,
and you can manage it entirely.
And all of that won't affect the
original version of the repository.
So if you ever look at open
source projects, projects
that many people on the
internet are contributing to,
very frequently there will be one
version of the repository that's
the version of the repository.
And different people that want
to contribute to that project
will each independently
fork that repository--
take their own version
of the repository,
make their necessary changes to it.
And when they like their changes,
when they'd like for those changes
to be merged back into the
original version of the code,
they'll submit what's
called a pull request.
And a pull request is
just a fancy way of saying
that you would like for
your changes to be brought
in from one branch of some
repository to some other branch
of the same repository, or
even a different repository.
So when you submit
project 0 for instance,
you'll do that via submitting a
pull request to the original version
of the repository.
And you'll often see pull
requests as a good way
of getting feedback or
comments from other people
that you're collaborating
with on projects.
They're an easy way of saying,
I've made these changes.
I would like someone
to review those changes
before we merge them into the master
branch of a repository, for example.
They're are a good
sanity check, in a way,
to take a step back and
take a look at the code
that you're about to merge before
you actually perform that merge.
So I'll show you an example of that now.
So over here, we set up a--
we had, on the lecture1 repository,
a master branch and a feature branch
where, on the feature branch,
I had added some new changes
and added some new code.
And now if I want to submit a
pull request-- in other words,
say, I like this new feature branch.
I would like for it to be
merged into the master branch--
I'll just click the Compare
& Pull Request button
on the right side of the feature branch.
And I'll just go ahead and click
the Create Pull Request button.
And so this is a
GitHub-specific feature that
lets whoever owns this repository
see that I am proposing
to make these changes to the code.
You can see what changes
I'm proposing to make--
remove this line, add that line.
And what this allows us to do is to
have a conversation about the changes
that I'm proposing to make.
It allows for people to request
that new changes get made.
And this is a common
paradigm, if you see projects
on GitHub, where people
will use the pull request
feature as a way of getting feedback
and working together collaboratively
on projects.
And so you'll get an opportunity
to play around with forks
and pull requests over
the course of project 0.
And you'll find more information
about that in the instructions.
But just wanted to give
you a look at it so
that you can get a sense for
what the interface looks like,
and ultimately, how that works.
But now let's take a step away
from Git and start going back
to actually designing web pages,
and structuring our web pages,
and organizing them, in particular,
by taking another look at HTML.
So last week we took a
look at the basics of HTML,
how we might structure a
website using nested tags.
If you remember, those tags took the
form of an open angled bracket, then
the name of the tag that we wanted,
and then a closing angle bracket.
And using just that simple syntax,
we were able to create lists,
we were able to add images into
the content of our web page.
But thus far, we've only been
interacting with a single page.
We had one something.html document
where we put in a bunch of tags.
And that rendered a web page
that displayed some contents.
But modern websites and
modern web pages nowadays
don't just display content,
and that's it, on one page.
They'll very often need to
interact with other pages,
in particular, by linking to other
pages such that you click on a button,
or click on a link, and that
takes you somewhere else.
So let's take a look at
how we might actually
do that if we wanted to
write HTML code to connect
multiple different websites together.
So what we'll take a look now
is we will look at links0.html.
And so what we see in links0.html
is just a standard HTML web page.
As we remember from before, !DOCTYPE
html just means this is an HTML5
document, a document written
in the latest version of HTML.
This html says this is the beginning
of the HTML content of the website.
Here is the header of the
website, the Information
that's sort of metadata to the page--
not stuff that's going to be displayed
in the main contents of the web page,
but information that's
helpful for the web browser.
In particular here,
we specified a title.
The title of this page is "My Web Page!"
And then, inside the
body of the web page,
we have this contents, which is how
we're going to be creating a link.
So here we have a, or
anchor, and then href.
And href just stands for,
what is the hyperlink
that we want to link to when someone
clicks on the contents of whatever
is inside that tag.
So right now it says, "Click here!"
And href="hello.html" means, when
someone clicks on Click here!
we should take the user to hello.html.
And so if we open up hello.html
and see what's in there,
that's just a web page that says
"Hello, world!" for example.
So now if I open up
links0.html, what you'll see
is, right now, just has a big,
blue link that says "Click here!"
And if I click on that link,
where I'm taken to is--
if you look in the URL, the
URL changes to hello.html.
And the contents of that
page is "Hello, world!"
And so by using that tag, we were
able to link to a different page that
was located in the same folder.
I had a links0.html file,
and also, a hello.html file.
And a href was my way of
saying, when I click here,
I want to link and go to
that other page instead.
And this hello.html
file doesn't just have
to be a file that's located on
my computer in the same folder.
It could be an external URL if I want to
link to an entirely different website,
for instance.
So if I want to link to
https://google.com for example,
and say click here, and
take that to Google,
now, if I refresh my links0.html
page and I click here,
now I'm taken to Google's home page.
And so I can link not only to
a file located on my system,
but I can also link to elsewhere
on the internet as well.
And in addition to linking
to a different file
or to an entirely
different web page, you
can even use these a href tags to link
to different places on the same web
page.
And this is becoming
increasingly popular
as more and more content
gets put on the same page.
And oftentimes when you
click on links, they're not
taking you to different
pages, they're just taking you
to different places on the same page.
So we'll take a look at an
example of that as well.
Here is links1.html.
So what you'll see is, in links1.html,
I have a whole bunch of sections.
So each section starts with a heading,
h2, for a reasonably large heading.
And each one has an ID.
And recall from last week that the
ID attribute of an HTML element
is just an easy way to give
an HTML element a name.
So I want to give this header the
name "section1" such that, later,
as we'll soon see, I can refer
to this h2 tag as section1,
the thing whose name is section1.
I have a paragraph that has some text.
I have a second section that's
called section2, another paragraph,
and then section3, with a heading, and
then contents underneath that as well.
So how do I now link to
different parts of this document?
Well, if we notice up
here, I have what--
I just called it a table of contents,
and then ul for unordered list.
And remember, li are
the elements contained
within an unordered list or an ordered
list, li standing for "list element."
And each one of these list
elements is, itself, a link.
We have that same a
ref syntax in that tag.
But the link, instead
of being a .html file,
starts with this pound symbol
where the pound symbol just means,
rather than link to an individual page,
link to something with a specific ID.
In particular, here, by
clicking on the section1 link,
this means, link to
whatever has ID section1.
And this means, link to
whatever has ID section2.
And this means, link to whatever
has ID section 3 such that now,
if I open links1.html,
you'll see a table
of contents and individual sections.
And if I make the window
small enough such that I
can't see all of the
sections all at once,
you'll see that if I go to the table
of contents and click on Section 1,
for instance, it'll automatically
jump down to Section 1.
The page didn't change.
I'm still on that same page.
But it jumps me down
to that first section.
And if I instead click on Section
2 by clicking on that link,
that'll jump me down to
Section 2 on the web page.
And likewise, clicking on Section
3 jumps me down to Section 3.
And the reason that this page
knows about all these relationships
is via that ID attribute, the fact
that every place I want to link to
has that ID identifying it as
section1, section2, section3.
And then my individual links can
then use those ID names to say,
here is where I want the page to link
to when I click on that individual link.
Questions about linking between pages?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Is it possible
more than one [INAUDIBLE]??
BRIAN YU: Good question.
So the question is, can the same
ID show up in more than one place?
And the answer is no.
In HTML, there is sort of a rule,
which is that an individual ID can only
appear once on any given page.
So you should never reuse the same ID
in two different spots on the same page.
IDs are meant to be unique.
So when I refer to something
by ID, there should only ever
be one of those things.
If we want to refer to a group
of things by the same name,
there's a different attribute
for that called "class."
And if you give multiple different
things the same class name,
then it's possible to refer to
a group of things all at once
by referring to that class.
Great question though.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
You won't be able to--
so the question is,
can we link to something
based on its class?
And the answer is that's
not quite going to work,
because you imagine we might have three
things that all have the same class
name.
And so if I link to it, the
web page isn't going to know,
which thing do I
actually want to link to.
So generally speaking,
when we link to things,
we'll want to link to the same
page based on their individual IDs.
Couple other notes about
HTML-- so those were links.
HTML has undergone a number
of different revisions.
So the latest version is HTML5.
Back in HTML4, if we wanted to organize
our website into different parts,
you might imagine that a more
complicated website might have
a header at the top of the website.
It might have a navigation bar,
whether on the left side of the website
or a banner across
the top, for instance.
It has some main content,
and maybe a footer
at the bottom that has copyright
notices, or other links, or whatnot.
In HTML4, you might have seen syntax
that looks something like this in order
to organize your website, where a
div, if you recall from last week,
is just a vertical
section of the web page.
It's just a generic
section of the web page
that has some name associated with it.
And we might have added class names to
this where we said, div class="header"
such that later, I could use CSS and
say, take anything that's a header,
and give it a dark green background,
and make the font size 36 points
or whatnot.
And we might have had a separate
div whose class was "nav"
for the navigation bar, a separate
div for individual sections of the web
page, and a separate div for the footer.
And this is still a
reasonably common paradigm.
But in HTML5, since this process
is so frequent in web pages,
there are actually new
tags that are added
to HTML5 that are increasingly
being used in more modern web
pages that simplify this process.
Rather than just have divs
that have class names that
are specific parts of the web page,
some parts of the web page now,
in HTML5, have their own tags such
that if you want to better organize
the header of your website into
one section, or the navigation
bar of your website
into one section, you
can use the header tag to say, this
is the header of the website, nav for,
this is the navigation
part of the website.
And the reason you might do this
is because, then, in your CSS,
for instance, you could say,
take anything inside of the nav
bar of my website, and give it these
particular stylistic properties
in order to make the navigation
bar render in a particular way,
for instance.
And so this can be a nice,
simpler way of helping
to organize your website in
a way that's easy to read
and is easily understandable.
These aren't the only new tags
that are introduced in HTML5.
There are a whole bunch.
I won't talk about them all.
But a couple that are
particularly of note
are audio and video tags,
which make it really
easy to embed audio
content into your web page
or embed a video into your web
page, and then also, this one
called datalist, which is increasingly
popular now as autocomplete on--
when we're typing on a
phone or on a computer,
becoming increasingly prevalent.
And I'll show you an example
of one of these datalists just
now, because it is quite a nice feature.
So one thing we looked
at last week was creating
a simple form where,
inside of a form, we
might want people to enter in their
name, and their email address,
and other information that
they would want to submit.
We haven't gotten, yet, to how we can
process information from that form
and do something meaningful with it.
But we talked about how to create a
web page that just displays a form
that people can enter information into.
So let's go ahead and take
a look at form.html now.
And what we saw before is this
part looks very similar to the form
that we saw from last time where
we have a form tag that just says,
this is going to be an HTML form.
And here on line 10,
we have an input field.
An input tag just says, this
is going to be a place where
someone can input information.
We named that input field, which
doesn't do anything for us just yet.
But you can imagine that we've seen
the value of naming things in the past.
When we name particular HTML elements,
that makes them easy to refer to.
And in the same way, naming
particular elements of our form
is going to make it easy to refer
to later such that, when someone
submits the form, we're going to
be able to write code that says,
get the name from the form that will
get at this specific input field.
Or get the user's password
from the form, which
will get at that specific input field.
The type attribute of this
input field is set to "text."
This is just text that we
want the user to input.
And the placeholder is "Name."
And likewise, for the password,
the type is "password,"
which is a slightly different type.
And we'll see what's different
about it in a moment.
And the placeholder there is
just going to be "Password."
Here we see a different type of input.
Here we're asking for a favorite color.
And the options are going to
be red, green, blue, or other.
And rather than just have them type
in something, this type of input
is a radio input--
so a radio box where there is
sort of a bunch of circles,
and you can click on one of them
to select which one you want.
This is a slightly
different form of form input
that might prove useful to you
depending on the type of form
that you're trying to create.
And here we just have
four different inputs,
one for each of those
different radio options.
And then finally, down
here, we have an input
that is going to represent what
country the person is from.
And so we named it "country."
And we associated it
with a particular list.
And so this is the new feature of HTML5.
I associate it with
the list "countries."
And immediately below
that, I have a datalist,
which is just going to be
a list of possible options
that will populate this form.
And we'll see what that
looks like in just a moment.
It's name is "countries" so that our
input field knows how to reference it.
And now we just have a
whole bunch of options,
one option for all of the countries.
We just got a list of countries, and
put them all into individual options,
and put them into form.html.
So now if I open up form.html, here's
what that ultimately looks like.
I have a place where
I can type in a name.
I have a place where I
can type in a password.
And recall that that password field
had a slightly different type.
The name field's type had type="text,"
just normal text that I'm typing in.
The password had type="password."
Browsers know how to
interpret type="password"
to mean something special,
to mean this is secure,
sensitive information
that they're typing in.
So when I start typing into this field,
it's just going to show up as dots.
It doesn't actually
show the actual text.
And that I got just by
saying type="password."
And the browser knew to
interpret that as secure password
information, stuff that shouldn't just
be displayed as text on the screen.
The favorite color radio button, I
had these for radio input options.
And that shows up this
way, where I can select
among these potential favorite colors.
And then for country,
because I had this datalist,
if I start typing in
"United," for example,
it's going to automatically fill
in with any matching elements
from that datalist, because I provided
the list of all the countries.
And now all I have to do is click
on the country that matches--
in this case, United States.
And that fills in the
category appropriately.
I could also click on that arrow to see
any of the matches that showed up there
as well.
And so datalist is one of
several new features in HTML5.
There are a whole bunch of
new tags, audio, and video,
and datalist among them.
We won't have time to
look at all of them.
But just wanted to give
you a taste for what's new
in the latest version of HTML.
And HTML continues to add
new tags and new features.
But one of the problems
is that browsers need
to support the latest versions of HTML.
So it isn't always the case that as
soon as there is a new feature to HTML,
that every web browser in the
world will suddenly support it.
Oftentimes, older
browsers might take longer
to support newer features of HTML.
But HTML5 is starting
to become widespread.
All the major browsers now support
the most important features of HTML5.
So you can start to use things like
audio and video embeds and datalists
in the websites you design
with reasonably high confidence
that whoever is looking at the web
page will be able to understand it.
Question?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
BRIAN YU: Good question.
So the question was, is it important
that, in all the projects in the class,
that it works on every
single different browser?
Generally speaking, the
languages that we're teaching,
HTML5 and the latest
version of CSS, you should
feel free to use even if much
older web browsers might not
support those features.
We'll talk a little
bit later in the course
about how you might go about making
sure that some of the features
will work even on
older browsers as well.
But for the sake of project 0, I
wouldn't worry too much about it.
OK, so that's HTML.
And now what I wanted to do was move
on to talk a little bit more about CSS.
So CSS, which stands for
Cascading Style Sheets,
was the tool that we used last
week to style up our website.
In the form we just saw,
everything was sort of black text.
It was all in the same font.
And it wasn't particularly
aesthetically pleasing.
And what CSS allows
us to do is have a lot
of control over how the
website actually looks,
over the colors, and the
fonts, and the layout,
and ways that things are organized.
And we're going to spend,
basically, the rest of the lecture
today talking about how to
make that website look good.
Because there's a lot that goes
into organizing the website
and styling the website
in such a way that it's
going to be visually appealing,
and that things are organized
the way that we want it to look.
And in particular, in
the modern day and age,
where people are looking at websites
on a bunch of different platforms--
looking at them on their laptops, and
on their tablets, and on their phones--
it's important to think about and
consider how different websites might
look on different platforms and to
make appropriate adjustments in order
to make sure that if you look at the
website on a computer, it looks good,
but it will still look good even if
you look at the website on a phone,
for example.
And so we'll explore some of
the tools and technologies
that we might use in order to do that.
But let's start by looking at some
of the more advanced features of CSS
to have even more control
over how it is that we
want to style our website in
order to have a lot of control
over that individual style.
So let's take a look at this example.
So this is an example that
is similar to something
we saw last week just to
give you a refresher on what
CSS looks like in terms of code.
We see that inside the
body, we have two headings.
Here's one big headline, and
here's a smaller headline.
Recall that h1 is the biggest headline,
h2 is the next biggest, all the way
down to h6.
And up here in the style section of the
page, we've included some CSS content.
And so here, what I
said is h1, comma, h2,
where the comma just means
I want to apply styling
to multiple different things.
to the h1s and the h2s.
I could have equivalently
said, h1s I want colored red,
and h2s I want colored red.
But oftentimes, if you find
yourself repeating yourself,
it's a good idea to look
for ways to simplify.
And this is a paradigm that we're going
to be returning to later on in this
lecture.
But to make this simpler
for now, we can just say h1,
comma, h2 to mean, I want this
styling to apply both to h1 tags,
the big headlines, and h2 tags, which
are the slightly smaller headlines such
that if I open up
multiple.html now, what I see
is the big headline, which is
red, and the smaller headline,
which is red as well.
But in addition to the
comma that just lets
us select multiple
different things, there
are a bunch of other
CSS selectors that let
us be very precise about selecting
particular parts of our website
that we want to style and
styling them in particular ways.
On these simple websites
that I'm about to show you,
they might seem a little bit trivial.
But as your websites
start to get more complex
and start to have a bunch of
different moving parts to them,
it can be very helpful
to be able to be very
precise in selecting particular
parts of your website
that you want to style in
particular ways and making sure
that only those elements get
styled in a particular way
as opposed to all of the elements
on the web page, for instance.
And so no need to worry
about memorizing all of this.
All the CSS selectors
are very well-documented.
And it's easy to look them up in order
to find a particular selector that
works for you.
But I'll show you these
now just to get you
a sense for what you can do with CSS
and the amount of control and precision
that you can have over
CSS selectors such
that they may serve as
inspiration as you go ahead
working on project 0 or other
websites that you want to be styling,
potentially, in the future.
So let's go ahead and
open up descendant.html.
And so what's happening here
inside the body of this website
is that we have a
couple things going on.
So inside the body of the
website, we have an ol,
where ol stands for ordered list, which
is just a list where things, instead
of being bulleted like and an unordered
list, are numbered-- thing number 1,
2, 3.
And the web browser will automatically
number those things for us.
And we have a bunch of list items,
so list item one, list item two.
And inside of this ordered list,
we have a list inside of the list.
So if you've sometimes seen
websites that have nested lists,
or lists that have a left side and then
an indented part that's a list within
the list, this is all this is, another
list inside of the ordered list that is
a sublist-- sublist item
one, sublist item two--
and then another list item that's
part of this original ordered list.
So if you think back last week to where
we talked about the DOM, that tree that
shows how different HTML elements are
nested within other HTML elements,
you can think of this as
the ol, the ordered list,
containing four different pieces, one
list element, another list element,
an ordered list, which, itself,
contains two list elements, and then
a final list element
in the ordered list.
And so what styling do
we want to apply to this?
Well, here we're saying that we
want to apply styling to ol li.
So there's no comma here.
It's just ol li.
ol stands for ordered list,
and li stands for list item.
And what styling the ol,
space, li is going to say is,
I want to style all of the
list items, the li's, that
are contained within an ordered
list, or all of the list items
that are descendants of the
ordered list, equivalently.
And so all of those list items I
want to color red, for example.
And so now, if I open
up descendant.html,
we see that all of the list items,
including the sublist items,
are all styled as red.
And so why did the sublist
items get styled as well?
Well, it's because the only
rule that this CSS is following
is that if there is a list item,
an li, that is a descendant of
or is contained within an
ol, an ordered list, then
it's going to be colored red.
And this list item here, even though
it's inside of an unordered list,
is still inside of this
broader outer ordered list.
And so it's going to be
styled as red additionally.
If I add another list that's
entirely outside of the ordered list
and say ul for unordered list--
and I might say, here is a second
list here, and here's another item.
So this is an unordered list
that's outside of the ordered list.
If I refresh the page now, this second
list is not styled in that same way.
Because these are, yes, list
elements, or list items,
li's, but they're not
contained within an ol.
And so as a result, they don't
get styled in the same way
as all of these
individualist list items do.
Questions about how that space operator
works to select just the descend--
any descendants of a
particular HTML element
and specify those, specifically,
as the ones to be styled?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
So the question is, if,
in this case, we were
to omit the li entirely and just say
ol, that I want it to be styled red,
would that do the same thing?
In this case, yeah.
Because if we style the ordered
list, everything within it
is ultimately a list item.
And so it's going to
be styled red as well.
But you can imagine
more complicated cases
where the outside tag might have a bunch
of different types of tags within it.
And if we only want to specify certain
elements within the outer element
to be styled, that's when
having a second thing after it
can often be helpful.
And we might take a look at
couple examples of that later.
So that worked for
selecting any descendants.
And the way to think
about how this is working
is that we have these
list items, which are--
you can think of as children of the
ordered list, and these list items
down here, which you can
think of as grandchildren
of the ordered list, where we
have the ordered list, and then
the unordered list, and within it
are the individual list elements.
What if I only wanted to select
the immediate children, but not
the grandchildren,
the ones inside of it?
And so for that case, what we want
isn't the defendant selector that
selects all of the descendants,
but rather a selector that
is just going to select, for
us, the immediate children.
And so let's take a
look at child.html now,
which is going to be
the same body contents.
We still have an ordered list
with individual list items
and a sublist contained within it.
But here's the difference in the style
tag, just a minor syntactic difference.
Rather than ol, space, li, we
have ol, greater than sign, li.
And not greater than
sign is CSS's syntax
for specifying an immediate child.
So ol greater than li
is going to only select
list items that are
immediate children, directly
descended from any ordered list.
And it's going to color those
as red and ignore anything else.
So if we open up that
website and take a look
at what that looks like by opening up
child.html, this is the result, right?
The immediate children of the
ordered list, the numbered items,
all show up as red.
But the sublist items,
the things that are
contained within the unordered
list inside of the ordered list,
those aren't styled.
Those are still colored
black, because they're not
immediate children of the ordered list.
They're grandchildren
of the ordered list.
And so I'll show you that code again
just so you can take a look at it
to get a sense for
what's going on there.
Questions about the distinction,
though, between the defendant selector
and the immediate child selector?
OK.
There are a couple
other selectors that are
useful to just see so that
you get a sense for what you
can do with which HTML and CSS styling.
One is going to be in attribute.html.
So in attribute.html here-- and all
this source code is going to be made
available after the lecture if
you want to take a look at it--
we have, here, a form where that form
is very similar to the types of things
we've already seen where we have
a input field for the first name,
an input field for the last
name, and an input where
the person looking at the web page
can type in their age, for example.
And what you notice
is slightly different
about these is that first name and
last name have a particular type.
Their type is text, their text
that we want the user to input.
And their age, on the other
hand, is going to be a number.
The type is number.
And what some web browsers will do
is-- when the type of a input field
is a number, is-- they will try to help
you restrict the valid inputs that you
can type it.
Have you ever seen a HTML
input form, for example,
where they're expecting a number, and
if you type the letter, nothing happens?
That's because the web browser might
know that the type of this input field
is a number.
And so I better not allow anyone
to type text into that input field.
Because it should only ever be a number.
And so that's what that's doing there.
But what that allows us to do is
style things in particular ways.
And so CSS also allows for styling
things based on individual attributes.
And so before, we saw how we
could style any generic tag.
But here what we're looking at is I
want to add styling to input fields,
but only the input fields where
the type of that input is text.
And I can use any attribute
name and value here.
It doesn't just need to be input types.
It can be any time where we've seen
attributes added to HTML elements.
So we saw, like, src for
images, or href for links.
These are all attributes that we can
use the attribute selector for in order
to style them in particular ways.
So here we said the input type is text.
And if it's text, I want the
background color to be red.
And if the input type is number, then I
want the background color to be yellow.
So I'm delineating between
different input fields based
on their individual
attributes to say, here
is the way I expect certain
attributes to behave.
So if I open up attribute.html
now, here's what I see,
where these are all input fields.
The only difference between them is
particular attributes that they have.
And first name and last name are
now places where I can type in text,
and their background color is red.
And age, because it
has a type of number,
is going to display a
background color of yellow.
I have allowed myself to be
more precise about the way
that I select elements
in order to style things
exactly the way that I
want them to be styled.
And ultimately, that's what CSS
selectors are designed to help you do.
They are designed to help you
be more specific about the way
that you work with CSS and the way that
you select individual elements to help
make the process of designing a
web page that looks the way you
want it to look all the easier.
So couple other things to look at--
let's take a look at
different types of selectors
that operate in different situations.
In particular, CSS has the notion
of what's called a pseudo-class.
And a pseudo-class is just a
special state of an HTML element.
Because a web page is not
just something that gets
displayed, and the user
sees it, and that's it.
The user is often interacting
with that web page.
They're hovering over things.
Their cursor is moving around the page.
And so we might want our web page
to respond to user interactivity--
that when a user hovers
over something, for example,
we might want that behavior of the web
page to change in some meaningful way.
So let's take a look at exactly that
example by taking a look at hover.html.
And inside the body of hover.html,
it's actually a very simple body.
There is very little happening here.
I have a button tag,
and it says "Click me!"
And that's it.
But now let's take a
look at the styling.
This is where things get interesting.
So inside the style of this web page
I have a couple things going on.
I've said, take the button.
And here are the things that
I want you to know about how
we should be styling this button.
It should have a width of 200
pixels, a height of 50 pixels.
The font size will be 24 pixels.
Those are just arbitrary
numbers that I chose
to make the button look a little nice.
And the background color of the
button is going to be green.
But here, this colon syntax is what
I call a pseudo-class representing
a specific state of the HTML element.
In particular, this is what happens
when the button is hovered on,
when the cursor moves over that button.
And in particular,
what I'm saying here is
that, now, I want the background
color to be orange instead.
So I went to change the styling of the
website based on a particular state
that an element might be in.
So if I now open up hover.html
and take a look at it,
right now it just says "Click me!"
It's a green button.
But as soon as my cursor
moves over the green button,
it changes to orange, right?
I have that hover pseudo-class
attached to this button such
that it knows that when something
hovers over it, the styling of it
should change.
So this allows the styling of
a website to vary depending
on how the user's interacting with it.
And so you may have
seen this type of thing
happen where, when you hover
over something that's important,
it changes color, or it grows,
or it does something different
with its styling.
And oftentimes this is
how it's working, just
pseudo-classes that are
placed on CSS elements
to make them behave in certain ways.
In addition to
pseudo-classes, CSS also has
what's called pseudo-elements,
which are ways of affecting
particular parts of an HTML element.
And so I'll show you a
couple examples of that now.
These are a little bit less common,
but are still things that may come up.
So I'll show you before.html right now.
And so in before.html, what I have
here is an unordered list of links.
Here's one link.
Here's another link.
Here's a third link.
And right now they all just link to #--
in other words, don't
really do anything.
We're not linking to
any external website.
But for each of these
links, these a tags,
I have this pseudo-element before.
And what this is saying is I want
to apply some styling that happens
before the contents of the actual link.
And in this case, the
content is slash 21d2,
which is a special hex
value for a Unicode symbol.
So these are symbols that you can't
just normally type on the keyboard.
But special symbols like emojis and
other symbols have particular codes.
This code, you'll see in a moment.
And then it says "Click here."
And the font weight of
this contents is before.
And so it might not be immediately
clear what exactly is going on here,
but I'll show it to you.
And then we'll come back
to the code so you can
take a look at what's really happening.
Let's open up before.html.
And what you see is three links--
one link, another link, a third link.
But all of them are prepended with
this arrow sign that says "Click here."
And so how did that happen
where all three of the links
have that additional information
at the beginning of it?
Well, these individual links only
said "one link," "another link,"
and "third link."
But all the magic is
happening inside the style tag
where I'm saying, for every link,
before the contents of that link,
I want you to add this particular
content-- in particular, this symbol,
and then the words "click here."
And I want the font weight of
that before element to be bold.
And the result of that is this, where
each one of those individual links
is prefaced with arrow sign, click here.
And so if you have a bunch
of different elements
that you all want to begin with certain
text or a certain symbol for example,
you might use colon, colon, before,
as we used here, or colon, colon,
after, which does the same
thing, but at end of the element,
in order to make those
modifications as well.
One other potentially useful one--
and then we'll take a short break--
is selection.html.
So inside selection.html, the body
of it is just one long paragraph.
But inside the styling,
I say p::selection.
In other words, when
something is selected,
I want that selection to
behave in a particular way
or have a particular styling.
In particular, I want
its color to be red,
and I want its background
color to be yellow.
So if I open up selection.html,
what I get is just some text.
But if I highlight that text, it
highlights in a very particular way.
It highlights where the text
I'm highlighting is red,
and the background is yellow.
Because I'm specifically
saying, I want, when
I highlight the contents
of this paragraph,
for the styling to appear
in a particular way.
And so that's something
that you can do as well.
And so a bunch of those CSS
selectors are summarized here.
We have the multiple element selector
where a comma separates two things
to say, I want styling to apply to
both of these things, the descendant
selector for when I want to select
everything contained within something
else, immediate child for immediate
children but not grandchildren
or great grandchildren of an element.
We didn't see this one, but
the adjacent sibling selector
lets you select something that comes
immediately after something else-- so
two elements that are sisters to each
other in the tree rather than one
being the parent or
containing the other.
We saw the attribute selector that let
us say that inputs that are numbers
should be treated as different from
text inputs, and then pseudo-class
for things like when I'm
hovering over an element,
and then pseudo-elements for saying
before the contents of a page
or after a contents of the page.
Again, no need to memorize all of that.
But these are just a
sample of the CSS selectors
that you can use in order
to have a lot more control
over the contents of your HTML page.
When we come back, we'll dive even more
into CSS, not looking at CSS selectors
specifically, but looking at
how we might take a web page
and make it more
mobile-responsive for example,
and use some more advanced CSS features.
But for now, we'll take a short break.
And we'll be back in a couple minutes.
OK, welcome back.
So now what we're going
to do is take a look
at how we can go about making
our web pages mobile-responsive.
In particular, responsive
design is generally
the idea of trying to
make sure that our web
page is going to look good regardless
of what platform we look at it on.
Whether that's a desktop machine, or
a laptop, or a phone, or a tablet,
or any other device, we want
the website to look good
across all of that variety of platforms.
And so when we start to
think about responsive design
and how to go about making the
website look good no matter what,
what are some things we
would need to think about?
What might be important to keep track
of when thinking about how things
look on a computer versus a phone?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
BRIAN YU: Making sure the
text responds right-- yeah,
different screen sizes
might adjust for--
might require differently-sized text
in order to make the text look good.
Sometimes if you look at older websites
that aren't really designed for phones,
and you try and look at it
on a phone, all the text
feels, like, squished
into the center of what's
called the viewport, the area of the
phone that you see web content on.
We'll talk about ways that
we can go about fixing that.
Good point.
What other things might
be relevant to consider
when we think about
going from bigger screens
to smaller screens or
different platforms
that websites need do exist on?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
BRIAN YU: Yeah, things
need to move around a bit.
You might need to-- it might not just
be a matter of making everything smaller
in order to fit on the mobile screen.
But if you've got a
desktop website that has
a bunch of different columns
worth of stuff, maybe three
columns of information, and you want
to shrink that down to a mobile screen,
now, suddenly, you can't just
squeeze all three columns
into the same narrow
window on the screen.
You might want to stack
the three instead rather
than have all three separate.
And so we'll talk about ways that we
can go about making those considerations
and making sure that our
web pages are able to adapt
to those sorts of different types of
platforms and different screen sizes.
And so the first strategy that
we're going to be using here--
will be a number of
different strategies.
But one strategy that will use
are what are called media queries.
And so a media query is a
specific way of assigning CSS
not to a particular HTML
element, but to a particular HTML
element on a particular type of media.
So that type of media might be
particularly-sized computers,
or particularly-sized phones, or
even the difference between how
you want a website to look when
you are writing the code for it
to appear on a screen
versus how you want
the website to look if someone prints
it out, for example, on a printer.
Because maybe when someone prints
your website out on a printer,
you want the content of
the page to look different
than if you were just
writing websites that were
going to appear on computer screens.
And you might want
those to be different.
And so let's take that
as a first example
and take a look at
our first media query.
And so what we'll take
a look at is print.html.
And so what we have here is, in the
body of our web page, three paragraphs.
So this is a paragraph.
This is another paragraph.
And then I have a third paragraph,
and I've added a class to it.
And that class is going
to be called screen-only.
That's just a name I made
up, but it's useful for me
to know that this is going to
be a paragraph that is only
going to show up on computer screens.
When I print it out, it's
not going to show up.
So this paragraph won't appear
when you print this page.
And you might want this if you
have particular instructions for,
like, click on this button
or click on that button that
are relevant when someone's looking
at your web page on a screen
but aren't very relevant
if someone wants
to print out the contents of
your web page, for instance.
And so how do I go about styling that?
Well, this is what the style
header looks like here.
I have this @media, which
means, create a media query.
I want to apply CSS styling, but
only in particular situations,
only in particular cases.
What case do I want to
apply the styling in?
Well, in this case, I said @media print.
In other words, this
styling, I only want
to apply when the media, or the medium
by which my web page is being viewed,
is it's being printed.
And then .screen-only-- remember
that dot is a way of specifying,
select everything with
a particular class name.
Down below we had a paragraph
whose class name was screen-only.
And here I'm saying, take anything
whose class is screen-only,
and said its display property to none.
And if you haven't seen this before,
display property being set to none
means, make it not visible.
In other words, it's
not being displayed.
And we'll see other examples
of the display property later.
But what's the result
of that going to be?
Well, again, I have three paragraphs.
Here's a paragraph.
Here's another paragraph.
And here's a paragraph that won't
appear when you print the page.
And if I open print.html, what
I see is those three paragraphs.
And on my screen, they
look totally normal.
There'd be no way to tell
that this paragraph is
any different from the
other two paragraphs.
But if I go to the File menu,
and I try and print this--
if I were going to print
this web page out--
then the result that I see in
this preview is that I see,
this is a paragraph.
I see this is another paragraph.
But that third paragraph
isn't there, right?
That paragraph is now being printed.
And in my CSS, I said,
when the media that I'm
trying to use when viewing
this page is a screen,
I want that paragraph to have
a display property of none.
I don't want that
paragraph to be visible.
And by doing that, I'm able
to control how that web
page appears on particular mediums.
So that allows me to make sure
that this paragraph doesn't
appear when I print the page.
But of course, printing
is just one example
of a different medium on which
I might be looking at content.
The more frequent case
nowadays is probably
that I have content being viewed
on differently-sized devices,
that I have a computer with a very
wide screen, a tablet with a slightly
narrower screen, a phone with a
screen even narrower than that.
And I want to make sure that my website
responds to those changes as well.
So how might I go about doing that?
Let's take a look at responsive0.html.
And in the body of this
website, it's very simple.
All it says is a headline that
says "Welcome to My Web Page!"
And that's the only content
of the web page in the body.
But now let's look at the styling.
What's going on here, I
have more @media queries.
But this time, instead of specifying
@media screen for, here's the media
for what style it should look like when
something is being displayed on screen,
or @media print for when
I'm printing something out,
I have @media min-width--
500 pixels.
And what that means is that
the styling that follows
is CSS styling that apply whenever this
page is being viewed in a window that's
at least 500 pixels wide.
And in particular, when the window
is at least 500 pixels wide,
I want the entire body of my web page
to have a background color of red.
Meanwhile, for @media max-width--
499 pixels, that's saying
the exact opposite,
that if I'm on a smaller window where
the maximum width of the web window
is 499 pixels or anything
smaller than that,
then I want the body's
background color to be blue.
And so this allows me to change
the styling depending upon how wide
or how narrow a particular web page is.
So if I open up responsive0.html, what
I see is "Welcome to My Web Page!"
And the web page background is red.
And so that tells me that, based
on the contents of my code here,
the background color of red should only
apply when the width of my viewport,
the width of my window,
is at least 500 pixels.
So what happens now, if I
try to shrink that website
and make it less than 500--
I can grab the end and just
shrink down this website.
And watch what happens.
It's still red.
But as soon as it shrinks below 500
pixels, it changes to blue, right?
Above 500 pixels, it's red.
Below that, it's blue.
And that's a first example of how we
might change the styling of our website
depending on how big or small the
screen that we're looking at it
happens to be at that time.
So what are some other examples of that?
What's a more practical use case?
So in reality, we probably
don't care all that much about,
we want the wider screen to have a
red background and the smaller screen
to have a blue background.
But we might care about something like
this, which is a little more involved.
But I have a body.
And right now my headline is empty.
It's just an h1, sort
of a empty headline.
But we're going to fill
it in with content.
But that content is going to differ
based on the size of the screen.
So here I've said @media min-width --
500, same as before.
When the width of my screen is at least
500 pixels, then before the h1 tag,
the first thing that should
show up in my heading
should be the content
"Welcome to My Web Page!"
But on the other hand, if the size of
my web page is 499 pixels or smaller,
then I want the content of my h1
tag to just be the word "Welcome!"
maybe because, on a smaller screen,
I don't want a longer headline that
might wrap onto two lines, for example.
I just want a shorter headline that's
going to look a little bit better
on a smaller screen.
And so what would that
ultimately look like?
Well, it's going to be the same
thing as the background color,
but just instead of changing
the background color,
we're changing the contents of what's
actually displayed on the screen.
So I open up responsive1.html.
And right now it just says
"Welcome to My Web Page!"
as if I had just had h1,
welcome to my web page, end h1.
But if I shrink the window now,
when it would have normally
needed to potentially wrap onto another
page and I go beyond 500 pixels,
the headline changes.
Now it's just "Welcome!"
There's no "to My Web Page,"
because, on the smaller screen,
I want the smaller headline to appear.
If I go beyond 500 again, go larger,
then the full headline comes back.
And so again, that's all
because of these media queries
that let me specify the min width
or the max width of the screen
that I want things to
render on and decide
how I want the CSS styling to appear
depending upon that screen size.
One other thing you'll notice up here
on line 5 is this sort of strange line,
meta name equals "viewport"
content equals "width=device-width,
initial-scale=1.0"--
so sort of complicated line.
All this line is saying-- and you'll
see this line in a lot of websites
nowadays-- is the
viewport of my web page
is just the visible area on the
computer screen, or the phone screen,
or whatever screen is being used to
view the contents of the web page.
And oftentimes in older websites, if
you tried to view a website on a phone,
it would just pretend that you were
rendering the website on a computer,
and render it as a wide display, and
then shrink it down onto the phone such
that all the text on the phone
was really, really small.
If you've looked at websites on your
phone, you may have seen this before.
All this is doing is a line
that's telling the browser
to adjust the viewport to make
sure that we're scaling it
to the width of the actual device,
that the width of the viewport
should be whatever the
width of the device is.
And as a result, that
will help to prevent text
from appearing really, really small
when you render it on a phone as opposed
to on a desktop.
This line is often just a good first
step to throw into your web page
when you want to make
it mobile responsive,
because that will help to make
sure that the sizing of things
appears appropriately.
But the key of what we're doing here
in order to make this responsive
is these media queries that are
allowing us to specify what CSS
gets applied under which circumstances.
And so this is just some of the
basics of how we can use CSS in order
to help allow us to style
websites in particular ways
depending on different devices.
We can also use particular CSS layouts.
And I'll show you a couple of these now.
Again, no need to memorize
exactly what's happening here,
but just to give you a sense
for what's available in CSS.
But before I move on, question?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
BRIAN YU: If you had both--
so the question--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
BRIAN YU: Oh, if you wanted to
specify both a minimum and maximum,
I think there is a CSS keyword that
allows you to combine two different
media queries-- so like, min-width--
300 and max-width-- 500.
And I think you can look to the--
I'd refer you to the
CSS documentation just
to look at how you would go about
structuring that media query.
What we're looking at here is a
tool built into CSS called flexbox.
And what flexbox is
going to allow us to do
is create a web page that
looks something like this.
So we have a whole
bunch of elements here,
and each one is labeled A, B, C,
D, E, F, G, all the way through L.
And there's 12 of them.
And what might we expect
to happen if we were
to shrink this web page down
and view it on a smaller device?
Well, what we probably want to happen
is we still want to see these squares,
but we don't want to have to scroll
too much to the left and right in order
to see all four.
We'd rather have these individual
cells rearrange themselves
as we shrink down the page.
And so watch what happens
when I shrink this page.
It originally shows me four in any
given row, and I have three rows.
But after I shrink it
down a little more,
it's going to just
show three on each row.
And now I've got four rows.
And if I shrink it down more,
it's got two on every row,
and now I've got six rows.
And if I shrink down
even more, now we've
only got one, where each thing is
just stacked on top of each other.
So this is what we were
alluding to a little bit
before, where if we have items
appearing in multiple columns of content
across the screen, we might
want those things to move around
as we begin to resize
the window in order
to make it more adaptable to different
platforms and different devices.
So what does that ultimately look like?
Here's an example of flexbox in action.
I have a container that's just going to
contain all of these individual divs.
Each one is just a letter
followed by some random text.
And here's the styling
that makes that all happen.
Inside my container, I'm setting
its display property to flex.
In other words, I want
this to be a flexbox that
allows the content to, in
this case, wrap around it when
it reaches the end of a line.
So you might imagine that it's like
if I had all 12 in one straight line.
But as I shrink down the screen,
I want the individual cells
to wrap onto the next line and
the line after that in order
to make room for everything to show
up within the width of my window.
And now I have this .container,
greater than sign, div.
Remember, that greater than
sign means immediate child.
So for any div that is immediately
the child of the container,
here's how I want it to display.
And this is just arbitrary.
I wanted the background to be green.
I gave it a font size.
I gave it some margin
and padding in order
to make it look the way I want it to.
And I specified how wide it should be.
But really, the key was this, this
display, colon, flex, flex-wrap, colon,
wrap.
This is what allows me to get that
flexbox to wrap around just like that.
One other style that I'll show you
that's useful when we're laying things
out is having a grid.
We might want a grid
sort of like a table that
displays information in a grid format.
And so that might look
something like this, where
I have a grid of individual cells--
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, all the way up to 12.
And I might have content
in each one of those.
And you might imagine
that this is useful
if you want some information in the left
side of the page and some information
on the right side of the page.
And notice, as I shrink this down,
the size of that third column
automatically adjusts in order
to fit the width of the page.
If I go beyond it, it
starts to get cut off.
But if I'm greater than a certain width,
that third column will adjust itself.
So how does that work?
I'll just briefly show you this.
And again, this code is all
available to you after the lecture
if you want to take a
look at it to get a better
understanding for how it works.
But inside the body of my website, I
have a div whose class is just grid.
And I call it "grid" arbitrarily.
And then within that grid
are individual grid items.
And here is 1 through 12,
all just one after the other.
So how did I take those
1 through 12 grid items
and make it appear in a
grid that looks like this?
Well, here's the CSS styling
that made that happen.
For the grid, the
background color is green.
I used display, colon, flex before
when I wanted things to wrap around.
Here I'm using display, colon, grid.
I gave it a particular padding.
Remember, padding is just
the spacing on the inside.
And I wanted the grid
column gap, or the space
between individual
columns of the grid, to be
20 pixels, and the space between
individual rows in the grid
to be 10 pixels.
And here is grid-template-columns.
This is what allows me to specify
how wide I want each column to be.
And here I've said the first
column should be 200 pixels,
the second column should be 200
pixels, and the third column
should be automatically generated.
Just however much space
you need to fill space,
that is how much space the
third column should take up.
If I instead change both the
second and the third columns
to be automatically
filled, then what I get
is column 1 that will
always be 200 pixels,
but columns 2 and 3 that will
now adjust themselves naturally
in response to how I move things.
And if I change all of them to auto,
for example, now all three of them
will just automatically respond to
me changing the size of the website.
And they will shrink and grow
accordingly in order to fit.
Question?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
BRIAN YU: Great question.
So the question is, how did
I get the spaces to show up
between the individual grid cells?
Those were two particular
CSS properties.
Here grid-column-gap was 20 pixels.
That's the space between
individual columns.
And grid-row-gap is
the space between rows.
If I change the row gap
to, like, 50 pixels,
for example, now there's more
space in between individual rows.
And so you can use the
column gap in the row gap
to control the amount
of space that shows up
in between the individual cells.
But ultimately, this is starting
to get a little bit complicated.
And realistically, it would be
pretty annoying if, every time we
wanted something to
wrap onto new pages, we
needed to remember exactly how
the flexbox worked and set up
the flexbox for ourselves.
But luckily, nowadays there
are all these CSS libraries
out there, which are ways that are--
CSS written by other
people that we can then
use them in order to
make our lives easier
when it comes to making our websites
mobile-responsive, for example.
And one of the most popular
libraries is called Bootstrap.
And that's the one I'm going
to be introducing you to now.
You'll get an opportunity to
work with it in project 0.
But Bootstrap is just an easy way
of giving you access to some CSS
that lets you make your websites
styled a little more nicely,
make them a little more
mobile-responsive right off the bat
without you needing to
do a whole lot of work.
And so if I open up nobootstrap.html,
this is just a simple website,
just like stuff we've seen before,
where I have a heading that says "Hello,
world!"
and then a paragraph of text.
And if I open up
nobootstrap.html, this is
what it looks like, same sort
of thing we've seen before.
If I want to add Bootstrap to
my file, all I need to do is--
in bootstrap.html, this
is the exact same website,
but I've added one extra line, this link
line where I'm linking a stylesheet.
I'm linking Bootstrap's CSS file, which
is located somewhere on the internet.
And if you go to
Bootstrap's website, you
can find this exact line that
you can put into your web page.
And now everything else about
my website stayed the same.
All I did was add Bootstrap's CSS.
And now if I open bootstrap.html,
the website looks a little bit nicer.
You notice that there's some
padding along the outside.
You notice that the headline is
in a slightly different font.
This is Bootstrap's default style
that you're welcome to change.
But that is Bootstrap's
way of just making
your website look a little bit
nicer, look a little bit more modern.
But the real power of Bootstrap comes
when you start to look at the way
that Bootstrap organizes
information and lays things out.
So Bootstrap's layout system uses a
column-based model where the website is
divided into--
or each row in the
website, you might think,
is divided into 12 individual columns.
And you can control how many
columns different things take up,
recognizing that 12 columns is sort of
the full width of your entire website.
So let's take a look at column0.html.
So inside the body of this website,
here's what we have going on.
I have a div whose class is row.
Row is a special class in
Bootstrap that just means,
this is going to be a
row of my page that's
ultimately divided into 12 columns.
And here are my individual
divs within that row
where each one has a class of col-3.
And col-3, in this case, just stands
for, this is a column that's going
to take up three
columns' worth of space.
So if I have a 12-column page, I can
have four things that each take up
three columns' worth of space.
And that's ultimately going
to make up my entire row.
So this is a section, another section,
a third one, and a fourth one.
And I've added some
styling to it in order
to make it look a little bit nicer.
I've added some padding on the outside,
a background color, and a border.
And you'll see what that
looks like in just a moment.
So if I open up column0.html,
you can see that, now, I've
got these four sections, these four
individual columns that are each
taking up three out of the 12 total
columns that are on the Bootstrap grid
layout.
And notice, if I shrink it down,
some of the spacing goes away.
You'll notice things
automatically adjust a little bit.
So it's designed to be very
mobile-responsive out of the bat.
I didn't write any of the code
or the CSS to help things resize
and rearrange when the
screen size changes.
Bootstrap's doing that all for me.
So that's four columns.
But really, what I would
like is for these columns
to move around depending
on the size of the screen,
that I don't just want
it to be four columns.
Because once it gets to a really
narrow device, these four columns,
if there's a lot of
content in them, this
is going to look really
squeezed together so to speak.
So what might I do about that?
Well, in this case, let's
take a look at columns1.html.
This is very, very
similar, almost the same,
with a couple of changes inside the row.
Before every class inside these divs
inside my row, we had a class of col-3
for, we want this column to
take up three out of the 12
possible columns that are present
inside of the Bootstrap grid layout.
In this case, I've done something
a little more sophisticated.
I said, "col-lg-3" and "col-sm-6."
In other words, on a large
screen where Bootstrap
has defined for me what
counts as a large screen
by taking a look at what typical
computer displays look like,
what mobile displays look like,
what tablet displays look like--
but on a large screen, I want this div
to take up three columns out of the 12
on my screen--
in other words, a quarter
of the total width.
But on a small device, I would
rather it take up six out of the 12,
or half of the total
width of the screen.
And likewise, I did the same thing for
each one of these individual columns
within this row.
And so on a large screen, we have
col-lg-3, large 3, large 3, large 3,
where each column will take up
three out of the 12 possible columns
in the Bootstrap grid model,
whereas on a small screen,
each one will take up half of the
total width of my Bootstrap grid.
So what does that look like?
What's the impact of this when I try
and render this website and look at it?
If I open up columns1.html, on a large
screen, it looks exactly the same.
I've got one column,
two, three, and four,
where each column is taking up three
out of the 12 available column spaces
that Bootstrap provides to me.
But as I make this smaller, what
you'll notice is that once it gets
to a certain point--
in this case, here--
it changes from four columns all
in a row to two columns on each row
where, before, here, on a
large screen, each column
was taking up three out of
the 12 possible columns that
were available in Bootstrap.
But on a smaller screen, each
one's taking up half of that width.
And the result of that is that
the latter two columns, which
don't fit within the 12, get moved onto
another line entirely of their own.
So I could have done this
using flexbox like I showed you
a moment before, where things
start wrapping onto other lines
as I start to reduce it.
But Bootstrap, which is
actually written using flexbox,
sort of abstracts that
away and lets us just
take advantage of defining how
wide we want our columns to be
on different size devices.
And Bootstrap takes care of the
rest of making sure that things get
rendered the way that we want them to.
Question?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
BRIAN YU: Question-- yeah, so Bootstrap
does define classes within it.
AUDIENCE: What happens if I [INAUDIBLE]?
BRIAN YU: Great question.
So the question is, Bootstrap defines
a whole bunch of these classes.
It defines row, and col-lg-3, and
col-sm-6, and so on and so forth.
What happens if I, in my CSS files,
am also using col-lg-3 or row as CSS?
And generally speaking, your web browser
is able to take multiple CSS files
and try and reconcile them somehow by
applying all of the styling together.
But if the styling
conflicts, if Bootstrap says
this row should have
this width, but you say
the row should have some
other width, then one of them
ultimately needs to take precedence.
And generally speaking, the
one that takes precedence
is the one that is more specific.
So if you had said that, I
want the styling to apply
to any row that is a child of some other
thing, then that will take precedence
over just a generic, I want rows
to be styled in a particular way.
But generally speaking, it's
a good idea to be mindful.
And if you were defining
classes of your own,
oftentimes it's a good idea to give
them different names from the ones
that Bootstrap does just to avoid
having that conflict at all.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
class in Bootstrap.
BRIAN YU: Correct, container
is a class in Bootstrap.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
BRIAN YU: Yeah, Bootstrap--
BRIAN YU: So if you want to
take the Bootstrap classes
and add your own styling
to them, you can sort of
override Bootstrap, so to
speak, by adding CSS code that
refers to Bootstrap's classes.
But you can add additional
styling of your own
to them to make them display the
way that you want them to display.
And you can experiment
around with that to see
how that ends up actually working.
But Bootstrap, in addition to
providing this grid layout,
also has a host of other features.
And we're not going have time
to go through all of them.
But I'll show you a couple
of interesting ones here.
For instance, Bootstrap makes it
very easy to create alert messages.
So these are some sample messages, just
generic news, good news, and bad news.
And in order to create those
alert messages, all I needed to do
was apply particular classes.
So the class alert and alert-primary
will automatically style something
as a blue alert message.
An alert alert-success will
automatically style it is a green one.
And alert, dash,
alert-danger automatically
styles it as a red message.
And so this makes it very easy
to add these alerts to my code,
because Bootstrap has already
written the styling for how to make
them display in a way that looks nice.
| if you're curious and you want to
use more of Bootstrap's elements,
you can go to Bootstrap's website,
which, I believe, is getbootstrap.com.
And if you go to their documentation
on Bootstrap's website,
you can look at all of their components.
So here, what we just saw
were Bootstrap's alerts.
You can see all of Bootstrap's alerts.
And here is the code that
you can just copy and paste
in order to create alerts
that look in a particular way.
Bootstrap also has special
styling for buttons,
buttons that appear in different
colors and different sizes.
And they tell you what
classes to add to your buttons
in order to make your buttons
styled in a particular way
to make them look a little bit nicer.
And there's a whole lot of
other features and styling
that Bootstrap adds.
You can just scroll through
this list and get a sense
for some of the features
that Bootstrap gives to you.
And by using some of
these features, you can
start to make your
website look a lot nicer
much more quickly by taking advantage of
the work that Bootstrap's already done.
So one last topic that I wanted to
talk about today with regards to CSS
and how we might go
about styling our website
is what happens when our stylesheets
start to get a little more complicated
and get a little more sophisticated.
So I want to take a look
at variables.html here.
And you'll see why it's called
"variables" in a moment.
But right now I have, inside of
variables.html, an unordered list,
a ul, and an ordered list, an ol.
And let's take a look at a sample
CSS file that I might use in order
to style this variables.html file.
I have ul, which is set to font-size--
14 pixels, and color is red,
and ol, which is font-size--
18 pixels, and color is also red.
So these two lists are going to be
displayed in different-sized fonts,
but I want their color,
ultimately, to be the same.
I want their color to
render as red either way.
What if-- and maybe that's because
the generic style of my website
is that I like the color red, and I want
my web page to render things as red.
But what if, later on down the
line, I decide, well, wait a minute,
I'd really rather that by list
be blue instead, instead of red.
In this case, I would need to
go back to two different places,
to the unordered list, and change the
color to blue, and the ordered list,
and change that color to blue as well.
And you can imagine, in a
more complicated website,
if I had dozens of different examples
of CSS styling in particular colors,
I might need to go through all of them
and change those individual colors.
And it might not be as drastic
of a change as red to blue.
It might be just a slight shade
of red that you want to change,
and you want to change it in
many, many different places.
And having to change it
independently on each separate line
is ultimately going to
start getting tedious.
And remember, we talked
about before, if you ever
find yourself repeating the
same thing over, and over,
and over, you should always think
about, is there a better way to do it.
Is there something else
we can be doing instead?
And if you're familiar with
programming and programming languages
like C, or Python, or
any other language,
then you might be familiar
with the concept of variables,
where we assign a
variable of value once,
and then we can reuse it multiple times.
And if we change that variable's
value, then that variable's value
is changed everywhere, so to speak.
And so what we're going to do now is
introduce an entirely new language
which is built on top
of CSS called Sass.
And what Sass is is
it's an extension to CSS
that gives us a little more power
and a little more flexibility when
it comes to designing CSS stylesheets
that lets us programmatically generate
stylesheets in a more advanced
and more powerful way.
But ultimately you'll see
that the concepts here
are just to make it easier to
generate the stylesheets that we
want to generate.
So instead of variables.css, I'm
going to look at variables.scss,
where .scss is the typical
extension for a Sass file,
which is going to be some specific
extension to CSS that we're going
to explore in a moment.
So what's going on in variables.scss?
Well, the first thing I do on
line 1 is define a variable.
We haven't previously had any variables
in CSS, because CSS, out of the box,
doesn't really support
the idea of a variable.
But Sass, this extension to CSS, does.
And so how does it work?
On line 1, I said $color--
all variables in Sass
begin with a dollar sign--
$color, colon, red.
So I'm defining a new variable.
It's called color.
And its value is going to be red.
And then, here's what's happening.
I have my unordered list,
whose font size is 14 pixels.
And the color-- instead of
saying red is the color,
I'm saying $color, meaning
$color was this variable that I
defined to be red before.
Whatever color that is, that's the
color I want my unordered list to be.
What about my ordered list?
Well, the font size is
going to be 18 pixels,
and the color is also
going to be whatever
the value of this color variable is.
And so by doing this, I get the
same effect-- an unordered list
that's 14 pixels in font size and red.
And same is true for the ordered list--
18 pixels in size, and the color is
also going to be red-- no different.
But I faced a problem.
Can anyone guess what the problem might
be if I tried to just use this code
and render it in the web browser?
Do we think it will work?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
BRIAN YU: Oh, is there, like, a
particular CSS property called color?
That's not going to
be a big deal for us,
but that's a good point, that we want
to be careful about naming things.
But ultimately our web browsers
are trained to understand CSS,
and they know how CSS works.
But web browsers don't, out of the box,
understand Sass, this extension to CSS,
where we have variables in there.
So our web browsers are
going to start to complain
if we just put this inside of a CSS
file and say we want this to render
as the styling for the website.
So what we need to do is take
this SCSS file, this Sass file,
and convert it into a CSS file.
And that's why there's a program
called Sass, which does just that.
And I'll show you how it works.
If I go into my variables
directory, what I have here is
a variables.scss file.
And if I run sass
variables.scss variables.css,
what that is going to do is it's
going to take my variables.scss file,
and it's going to compile
it-- turn it into--
a CSS file that my web browser is
going to be able to understand.
So I press Return.
That compiled it.
And now if I take a
look at it, I see I now
have a variables.css file,
which I didn't have before.
And I also have this
additional map file.
You don't need to worry
too much about that.
But if you're curious, that's
just a way for your browser
to understand the relationship
between the CSS and the SCSS file
in case it wants to figure out--
it's useful for debugging or
figuring out what line something came
from in the original file.
But let's look at this variables.css
file, which I didn't create.
It was generated for me by Sass.
What does it look like?
So it looks, ultimately, like this.
And it's exactly what my
previous CSS file looked like.
But it substituted that
color variable with the name,
or whatever value that color
variable was actually assigned to.
So color is now red.
Color is now red in both the
unordered list and the ordered list.
The fact that the curly brace is on
the same line instead of on a new line
like we've been doing before
is just that stylistic choice.
It doesn't actually make a difference
on the way that the page renders.
But what I've done is I've used
the variable from the SCSS file
and compiled that file into a CSS file.
And now this is something that my web
browser can ultimately understand.
So now if I go back to variables.html
and open up variables.html, what I get
is an ordered list where
the unordered list items are
smaller than the ordered list items.
But all of the list items are red.
And now, if I wanted to change this--
if I wanted to change the color from red
to blue, for instance, rather than
change it in two different places--
or, and you imagine, in
a larger-scale program,
potentially dozens or hundreds of
places across your web application--
all I need to do is change
this $color variable.
I change it from red
to blue, for example.
And if I open variables.html,
now it's still red.
I changed it to blue, but the styling
of the list items is still red.
Why is that the case?
Why did that happen?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
BRIAN YU: I need to recompile it, right.
Because this HTML website is
only looking for variables.css.
It doesn't know anything
about variables.scss,
which is the file I've
actually been working with.
So I need to run sass
variables.scss variables.css.
That's going to recompile my CSS file
such that when I now refresh the page,
now everything is blue.
Now, as you're developing
with SCSS, you might
imagine that it's going to start to
get annoying fast, where every time you
make a change to a
SCSS file, you're going
to need to recompile it back into CSS.
So Sass has some built-in features to
help make this a little bit easier.
One is that Sass can watch a file--
in other words, keep track of the file,
or even a directory full of files--
and any time any of them changes,
automatically recompile the CSS file.
So if I said sass
--watch variables.scss,
and any time a change is
made to variables.scss,
compile it to variables.css, now
Sass is watching for changes.
So now if I go back here and change
the color to green, for example,
and I save that, if I
check back here, Sass
has automatically detected that I've
made a change to variables.scss.
And it's written me a new
version of variables.css.
So without me needing to manually
go in and recompile that SCSS file,
I can refresh the page.
And now all of the list items are green.
So that's marginally
better, that instead
of needing to recompile the Sass
file every time I make a change,
I can just tell Sass,
watch all of my SCSS files.
And whenever any of them change,
automatically compile it to CSS for me.
And an additional feature is that
many website deployment systems,
GitHub Pages included, have built-in
support for Sass such that if you push
an SCSS file to GitHub Pages
in project 0, for instance,
GitHub will automatically take care of
the process of compiling that Sass file
from a .scss file to a .css file such
that when someone goes to your website,
they will see the resulting CSS
style applied to your website.
And so many system nowadays
have built-in support for SCSS.
They make it easy for
you to use Sass in order
to have a little bit more
control over your styling
in order to make websites really look
the way that you want them to look.
Questions about Sass so
far and what we've seen?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
BRIAN YU: Great question.
Do you need to install anything
in order to run the sass command?
Yeah, you'll need to
install Sass in order
to make any of that-- the command
line sass command work that does
the compilation from SCSS files to CSS.
If you never want to do
the compilation yourself--
if you want to just rely on GitHub
to do that compilation for you--
then you don't need to install anything.
You can just push an SCSS
file to GitHub Pages.
And GitHub Pages will, on
its own, convert it into CSS.
But if you want to test
that compilation locally
to see what the resulting CSS looks
like, then you'll want to install Sass.
It's a freely available,
pretty small piece of software
that you can just install
onto your computer
the same way you installed Git or other
software in order to make that easier.
Other questions?
Yeah.
AUDIENCE: What if I
had multiple CSS files,
like if we downloaded the Bootstrap
CSS file and I [INAUDIBLE] from that?
BRIAN YU: Great question.
So the question is, how
does Sass work when we're
dealing with multiple different files?
Sass has a built-in
command that actually
lets you import existing CSS from
a different file into a Sass file.
So there's built-in support for
multi-file stylesheets built into Sass.
We won't see any examples
of that in this lecture.
But if you go to the
Sass website, you'll
find examples of how
they're able to incorporate
different files into
the same file in order
to use variables that are
defined in a different file
in a separate stylesheet.
Great question though.
One more question?
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
BRIAN YU: Great question.
So the question is, when
you're linking the file,
do we want to link the
CSS file or the SCSS file?
We always want to link the CSS file,
because the CSS file is the only one
that the browser actually understands.
Google Chrome, out of the box,
doesn't know how to take a Sass file
and understand what the variables mean.
It only understands the CSS file.
So what we need to do is
say, reference the CSS file,
and then just make sure that
somehow, either us doing it ourselves
or letting GitHub
Pages do it for us, get
that Sass file compiled down
to CSS such that we can then
use it for our own purposes.
Excellent question though.
So those are variables in Sass.
But what other features
does Sass give us?
How else can we make this
a little more powerful?
Well, one other feature
that's very helpful
is nesting different CSS
selectors within each other.
And I'll show you an
example of that now.
So here is nesting.html.
So inside the body of nesting.html,
I have a big div, inside
of which is a paragraph
inside the div, and also
a list inside the div, an unordered
list with three list items
that are all inside of this div.
And outside of that
division of the site,
I have a paragraph that's
outside of the div and a list
that's also outside of the div--
so sort of a trivial,
contrived example, but just
going to show you a bunch of
different hierarchies via which we
might organize different HTML elements.
And I want to style them
in a particular way.
So let's take a look at nesting.scss.
And so here's the
contents of nesting.scss.
I have div font-size--
18 pixels.
And then within the div's curly
braces, I have an additional p.
And what that p is
standing for is that I
want this styling to apply to any
paragraphs that are inside of a div.
Now, notice that this
isn't anything we couldn't
have done before with just regular CSS.
We could have said, on a
different line, div, space, p
and then color equals blue to
say paragraphs inside of a div
should be colored blue.
But nesting things
within each other just
helps to organize things a little more.
Especially as our stylesheets start
to get longer and more complicated,
we might find it easier to
organize our code into something
like this where we can say, all
right, how are we styling the div.
Well, the font's going to be 18.
Any paragraphs within it should be blue.
And any unordered lists
within it should be green.
And that just helps to organize
our styles a little more
such that, as they get longer,
it gets easier to look at
and easier to maintain.
So when I compile that using
Sass, which I've already done,
I'll show you with the
resulting nesting.css file--
or actually, I'll do it now.
I'll go into my nesting directory
where I have a nesting.scss fild.
I'll go ahead and compile
nesting.scss to nesting.css.
And we'll take a look at
what that file looks like.
And what it's ultimately
done, it's done exactly what
we would have done before if we
didn't have Sass at our disposal.
It said div's font
size is going to be 18.
And then where, before, we
just had p inside of the div,
it's changed that to div, space, p.
In other words, all paragraphs contained
within a div are going to be blue,
and all unordered lists within
the div are going to be green.
But instead of needing to
specify this div every time,
we were just able to enter scss,
have a slightly simpler, slightly
easier to look at interface
that tells us how things
are going to be styled inside the div.
So if I open up nesting.html, what the
result is is that the paragraphs get
styled as blue, the
list items get styled
as green, but only the ones that
are inside of this part, which
was that original div.
And anything outside of it doesn't get
styled in that particular way at all.
So that nesting feature is just
another nice to have that Sass offers.
Sass offers a number of
different other features.
But the last one that we'll take a look
at today is the concept of inheritance.
And inheritance is something you
may be familiar with if you've
done programming before in
object-oriented programming
languages like Java or Python.
But inheritance in
the context of Sass is
used to refer to when you
have some general styling
that you might want to apply to a
whole bunch of different things,
but each of those
different things you might
want to be styled in a
slightly different way.
So if you think back to
Bootstrap for example,
where we saw those alert messages
in Bootstrap where we had--
I'll open it up--
where we had a blue alert, a
green alert, and a red alert,
what if we wanted to create this
sort of interface for ourselves
without using Bootstrap where we
wanted different alert messages that
were different colors?
Well, you might imagine there's a
lot of styling that goes into this.
There is a particular
font that they're using.
There's a particular
font size that they're
using for all of these alert messages.
But also, all of these alert
messages are different.
This one's blue, this one's
green, this one's red.
And as a result, they need
slightly different CSS styling.
But they're fundamentally very similar.
So there's a lot they share in common.
If we were to write
out the CSS by hand, we
might have a lot of
repetitive styling where
we have the styling for the
first alert message that
got a lot of the same stuff, then
a blue information, same thing
for green and red.
But with SCSS, we can use
the concept of inheritance
to factor out all of those
commonalities in order
to make it easier and
more efficient to generate
CSS that lets us have
styling that inherits
from some overarching property.
And so let's take a
look at what that looks
like by opening up inheritance.html.
So what I have here is, without using
Bootstrap, I have three different divs.
This is a success message.
This is a warning message.
This is an error message.
One's classes is success.
One's class is warning.
One's class is error.
So those are my three classes
that I have to deal with.
And I want to style
them in a particular way
so they show up sort of
like the Bootstrap alerts
that we were looking
at just a moment ago.
So let's look up at inheritance.scss
and see what's going on here.
So what I have here is this %message.
And percent isn't something
we've seen before.
It's something specific to Sass.
And it lets us define,
effectively, a template, something
that other things are
going to inherit from.
And this is just going
to be a generic message--
whether it's a success,
of a failure, or an info
message, just a generic message.
And that message has a
particular font family.
It's going to be a sans-serif font.
It has a particular font size, 18
points, and it's going to be bold.
That message is going to
have a border around it,
a 1-pixel solid black
border around that message.
And it will have certain spacing,
20 pixels worth of padding,
and then 20-pixel margin.
And that styling, I want
it to apply to all three
of my different categories of messages.
Success messages, and error
messages, and info messages
alike all should have that same styling.
And so how do I do that?
Well, this is the code
that I need, now, in Sass,
in order to define those three classes.
My success class, I just
say, extend message.
Take all the styling from the
message before, and use it.
But let's additionally add that the
background color is going to be green.
Likewise, for the warning
message, let's extend the message.
It's going to have the same
style properties as the message.
But the background color is orange.
And same with error, except now,
the background color is red.
If I now compile that
down to CSS, the result
is that I get CSS code that applies
this generic styling to all successes,
warnings, and errors, and this
specific background color to success,
and a specific background
color to warnings,
and a specific background color to red--
to errors.
And again, none of this is stuff that
we needed Sass to do, but using Sass
makes it a little bit easier.
It's a little bit of a nicer semantic
to say, here's a generic message,
here's the styling for that message,
and here are specific success, warning,
and error messages that
are going to extend
or inherit from that
message in order to add
additional information,
the result of which
is a CSS file that we could
have written ourselves
but that gets generated
from the SCSS file.
So if we now open up
inheritance.html, this is what we get,
a success message, a warning
message, an error message.
We see the spacing around each.
We see the font size and the font
style that we wanted it to be.
But the difference comes
in the different classes.
One is a success message,
one is a warning message,
one is an error message.
And so those different types of
messages have different CSS styling
applied to them.
And as a result, they appear
a little bit differently.
So questions about any of
the Sass tools that we've
seen so far, whether it was variables,
or nesting elements within each other,
or using inheritance to
allow a generic style
to be applied to multiple different
types of classes, or IDs, or elements?
OK, if questions do come
up, feel free to reach out.
And feel free to post in
the Slack and ask questions
as you begin to dive into project 0.
In project 0, you'll have
more of an opportunity
to experiment with some
of this, to use Bootstrap,
to make your web page mobile-responsive,
and to begin to use Sass in order
to create more advanced, more
sophisticated stylesheets.
Next week we'll dive
into a look at Python,
and how we actually create web
applications by writing in Python,
and using some of the HTML and CSS
we've looked at in the last two weeks
in order to do so.
But for now, that's it for Web
Programming with Python and JavaScript.
Thank you all, and
we'll see you next week.